Luther-Bagby collection, Inclusive: 1821-2001, Bulk: 1890-1970
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Luther-Bagby collection
Inclusive: 1821-2001, Bulk: 1890-1970
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1337
Cooper, Thelma Lou Smith; Harrison, Helen Bagby; Luther, John Hill, 1824 - 1903; Smith, Harley; Smith, Alice Bagby
122 document boxes and 7 oversized boxes.
The Luther-Bagby collection consists of correspondence, literary productions, financial documents, photographs, and scrapbooks generated or collected by Luther, Bagby, or Smith family members, primarily pertaining to the Baptist mission experience in Brazil and throughout South America.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
John Hill Luther (1824-1903) was born in Rhode Island. He was a graduate of Brown University and Newton Theological Seminary. At a young age he had longed to be a missionary, but as an adult he became pastor in Beaufort County, South Carolina. In addition to being a pastor, Luther became a tutor in the home of Benjamin Jaudon of Robertville. One of the Jaudon children, Anne, later became his wife. John and Anne were married in 1854 August. After a brief time as pastor of several churches in South Carolina, John and Anne moved to Kansas City where John opened a school for girls, the “Young Ladies Seminary.” He served as the president of the Seminary from 1858-1861, and also pastored several churches in Missouri. In 1865 Luther established a Baptist paper, which he called the Missouri Baptist Journal. It later became consolidated with the St. Louis Record and was known as the Central Baptist, which was recognized by the Baptist General Association as the official Missouri Baptist state paper. In 1871, William Jewel College conferred on John Hill the honorary degree of Doctor of Divinity, recognizing him as a “foremost educator.”
During the Civil War and Reconstruction the family moved often but eventually felt the need to move to a more permanent location. Family members encouraged them to move to Galveston, Texas, where Luther became pastor of the 2nd Baptist Church for a year. In 1878, Dr. Luther accepted the presidency of Baylor Female College at Independence, TX. The Luthers had six children, three of whom died in infancy, and a son died during in his teenage years. The two surviving children were both daughtersDLAnne, born in 1859, and Zollie, in 1865. In 1886, Baylor University moved the male students to Waco. Dr. and Mrs. Luther were asked to move Baylor Female College to Belton, where he continued as President until 1891. Baylor Female College eventually became the University of Mary Hardin-Baylor (UMHB).
Zollie Luther, the Luther’s youngest daughter, married William Goodrich Jones, who was a banker in Temple, Texas. They had three children, Luther, Riette, and Doris Goodrich Jones. Anne Luther, the Luther’s eldest daughter, served as dean of the Baylor Female College during her father’s presidency. Anne also taught mathematics and represented the institution at State Baptist Conventions. It was during one of these conventions, in Calvert, Texas, that she met William Buck Bagby, who, like Anne, felt a call to foreign missions. William was born in 1855 in Coryell County, Texas. His family moved to Waco, Texas, when he was eight years old. William became a Christian while listening to a sermon from Dr. Rufus Burleson. He attended Waco University as the first theology student in the newly established theology department. William Buck Bagby and Anne Luther married in 1881.
In 1881, William and Anne were appointed by the Foreign Mission Board (FMB) of Richmond, Virginia, and left for the mission field, becoming the first permanent Baptist missionaries in Brazil, South America. Their work in Brazil constituted one of the longest tenures of any couple in Southern Baptist Missions. The Bagbys founded a church in Bahía in 1882, the first Brazilian Baptist Church, and another in Rio de Janeiro in 1884. The churches were successful, and several more were founded in the larger cities of Brazil. The churches were led by Brazilian pastors, trained by the Bagbys and other Baptist missionaries. Rio de Janeiro became the center for Baptist work in southern Brazil. In 1901, having worked in Bahía and Rio de Janeiro for several years, the Bagbys moved to São Paulo, where Anne was primarily responsible for the establishment of a school, Colégio Batista Brasileiro, that included a boarding school for girls. William continued to evangelize and organize churches throughout the southern part of Brazil. William and Anne had nine children, two of which died as infants. In 1912, their son Willson drowned while trying to save a friend. Another son, Oliver, moved to California after initiating studies at the University of Texas Medical School in Galveston, Texas.
The eldest Bagby child, Ermine (1881-1939), married Sidney Sowell, of Fluvanna County, Virginia. They served together as Baptist missionaries and educators in Argentina. They had four children: Maurice, Ben, Anne and John David. Anne Sowell Margrett, a University of Mary Hardin-Baylor graduate, was appointed a missionary by the FMB and became director of the Baptist Training School for women in Rosario, Argentina. Later, this Training School was moved to Buenos Aires where it became part of the Seminario Internacional Teológico Bautista.
The other four Bagby children served as missionaries in Brazil DLTaylor Crawford Bagby (1885-1954), Alice (1896-1973), Helen Edna (1900-1993), and Albert Ian (1902-1988).
Taylor Crawford (known as T.C.) married Frances Adams of Virginia, and both served as missionaries in Brazil. T.C. was especially active in organizing and pastoring Baptist churches in southern Brazil. They had seven children: Samuel, Kathleen, Luther, William, Priscilla, Jimmy, and Anne. Samuel became a pastor and Anne has served as missionary and educator in South America and Texas.
Alice Bagby Smith graduated from Baylor College in Belton (now the University of Mary Hardin-Baylor), and Southwestern Seminary Training School. She was appointed by the Foreign Mission Board as a missionary to Brazil to work in the school in São Paulo. She met Harley Smith, a Baylor University and Southwestern Seminary graduate, and they married in 1922 in Waco, Texas. The Smiths went to Porto Alegre in Rio Grande do Sul in Southern Brazil to work in the mission field there. The Smiths founded the Colégio Batista Americano Brazileiro in 1926 in Porto Alegre, to prepare students to be Christian leaders and witnesses. Harley was also the pastor of the Igreja Batista Central, a church that he and Alice helped to organize in Porto Alegre. In 1945 Harley and Alice resigned from the mission board to become independent missionaries, but they remained in the same area and continued with much of the same work. Harley and Alice moved to Waco in their last years, where Alice died in 1973, and Harley passed away in 1976.
The Smiths had three children: Helen Frances (1924-), Paul Bagby (1928-), and Thelma Lou (1936-). Helen Frances, eldest daughter of Alice Bagby and Harley Smith, graduated from Mary Hardin-Baylor in 1946. In 1947, Dr. Gordon Singleton, president of UMHB, performed the marriage ceremony for Helen Frances and Jimmye Hillman in 1947. Dr. Hillman spent his career as a distinguished international agricultural economist at the University of Arizona in Tucson, Arizona. They have three children: Brent, Brenda, and Brad. Paul Bagby Smith married Gloria Painter in 1950 and had three children, Jerry Paul, Jena Lesa, and Jane Noel. After Paul and Gloria divorced in 1956, Paul remarried in 1958, to Alba Ferrer of Venezuela. They also had three children: Patricia, Paul Harley, and Veronica. Paul was in the oil business, which took them to various places around the world, including Chile, Ecuador, and Venezuela. Paul and Alba now live in Miami, Florida. Thelma Lou graduated from Baylor University and the University of Texas. In 1959 she married William F. Cooper, graduate of Baylor University, Southern Baptist Theological Seminary and Indiana University. Bill is the son of William Lowrey and Catherine Cooper, missionaries to Argentina. William Lowrey was the president of the Seminario Internacional Teologico Bautista in Buenos Aires. Catherine served as music instructor and choir director at the Seminario. They served in Argentina for 35 years. In 1965, William and Thelma moved to Waco, where William was on the faculty of the Philosophy Dept. of Baylor University and was Dean of the College of Arts and Science for 9 years. Thelma was on the piano and piano pedagogy faculty of the School of Music of Baylor University. In 2006, she was inducted into the University of Mary Hardin-Baylor Hall of Fame as a distinguished musician. They have three children, Richard, Jonathan, and Dorisanne.
Helen Bagby, a graduate of Baylor College in Belton was appointed as a missionary to Brazil and was active in the school in São Paulo. She later became a teacher and principal of the school in Porto Alegre. In 1939, she married William Coleman Harrison from Kentucky. Harrison was appointed as missionary to Brazil and worked in various parts of Brazil as a pastor, professor, school principle, and mission treasurer. After he and Helen were married, they moved to the state of Pernambuco to work in the Baptist Seminary in Recife, the capital of the state. They had two children, William Bagby and Alice Ann, and adopted a third, Helga. William Bagby worked for the United States government, while Alice Ann has been an educator in Texas and Colorado.
Albert Ian, the Bagby’s youngest child, graduated from Baylor University and Southern Baptist Theological Seminary in Louisville, Kentucky. He married Thelma Frith, who had worked as an independent missionary with the Smiths in Porto Alegre. They were appointed by the FMB as missionaries to Brazil, where they settled in Porto Alegre, as teachers and administrators in the Colégio Batista Americano Brazileiro. Albert also pastored several churches. They had three sons: Albert Jr., Daniel (both Baylor graduates) and Ronald. Albert Jr. had a distinguished career as professor of Spanish and Portuguese at the University of Texas at El Paso. Daniel served as pastor in Indiana and in Waco, Texas, at Seventh and James Baptist Church, before accepting a professorship in Pastoral Care at the Baptist Theological Seminary in Richmond, Virginia. Ronald has been an educator in Gadsden, Alabama.
William Buck Bagby died in 1939 in Porto Alegre, Brazil. His wife Anne Luther died in Recife in 1942 December. By 1939, when William Buck Bagby died, Brazil had 778 churches with 68,731 members. For over 50 years, the family had prepared the way for continued growth of the Baptist churches and schools in Brazil and Argentina.
Scope and Content
The Luther-Bagby collection begins in 1821 and ends in 2001. The earliest materials are primarily biographical materials about John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther's ancestors. The bulk of the collection dates from the 1890s through the 1970s. Also present in the collection are notes from donors providing insight into the collection, such as what year a piece of undated material might have been written. The largest series in the collection is Series III. Smith Papers which includes considerable correspondence documenting the Baptist missionary experience in Brazil, as well as life in Texas. Throughout the collection there are connections to the history of Baylor University and the University of Mary Hardin-Baylor. These connections span from John Hill Luther's involvement in Baylor Female College to the wedding of William Buck Bagby and Anne Luther Bagby at Independence, Texas, to letters home from students at Mary Hardin-Baylor College and Baylor University.
The Luther-Bagby Collection reflects the activities of the John Hill Luther and William Buck and Anne Bagby families, who have been part of the early history of Baylor University, the University of Mary Hardin-Baylor, the Baptist denomination, and Baptist missionary life for five generations. The bulk of the collection consists of personal letters and documents of three families in particular: John Hill and Anne Jaudon Luther, William Buck and Anne Luther Bagby, and Harley and Alice Bagby Smith. There are additional letters from other members of the Bagby family. These families were particularly involved in founding Baptist churches and schools across southern US, Brazil, and Argentina throughout the 1880s and into the 20th century.
Arrangement
The Luther-Bagby collection was organized prior to this finding aid using various inventories and partial finding aids, but with no document that inventoried or listed the entirety of the collection. Many of the existing folder titles were kept and the existing arrangement was maintained as much as possible. The first three series of the collection contain materials that are grouped according to the family. The last three series are organized by material type. Brief archival description is also included as appropriate in the series and subseries Administrative/Biographical History.
Currently, the Luther-Bagby collection is arranged in six series: I. Luther Papers, II. Bagby Papers, III. Smith Papers, IV. Literary Productions, V. Photographs, and VI. Scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1337. Acquired 1975-11-21
Related Resources
Items in related collections
John Hill Luther
William F. Cooper
Related references
Harrison, Helen Bagby. The Bagbys of Brazil. Crawford, Tex.: Crawford Christian Press, 1954.
Lancaster, Daniel B. The Bagbys of Brazil: the life and work of William Buck and Anne Luther Bagby. Austin, Tex.: Eakin Press, 1999.
Odom, Harriet Aileen. "The church at work in Brazilian society through Dr. and Mrs. W.B. Bagby." M.A. thesis, Baylor University, 1952.
Pitts, William L. "Bagby, William Buck." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 August 28.
UMHB: News and Events. "Archive: Dr. Cooper to be Inducted into UMHB Hall of Fame." University of Mary Hardin-Baylor. University Website. Accessed 2013 August 28.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Bagby, Anne Ellen Luther, 1859-.; Bagby, William Buck, 1855-.; Luther, John Hill.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor Female College -- History.; Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University (Independence, Tex.) -- History.; Mary Hardin-Baylor University.
Subjects
Baptists -- Missions -- Brazil.; Baptists -- Sermons.; Baptists -- Texas -- History.; Genealogy.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Essays.; Financial records.; Interviews (Sound recordings); Legal documents.; Manuscripts.; Periodicals.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.
- Luther Papers, 1821-1939; 1; Four document boxes and one folder of oversized material.
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains four boxes of materials about the Luther family, including correspondence, literary productions, and legal documents. The bulk of the materials in this series focus on John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther as well as their daughters, Anne Luther Bagby and Zollie Luther Jones. Main themes in the series include John Hill Luther's writings such as speeches and essays, and the Luther family's involvement with Baylor Female College.
  - Correspondence, 1872-1903; 1
    Description of Material
    This subseries contains correspondence to John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther from various family members in addition to a small amount of outgoing correspondence from the Luther family.
    - To John Hill Luther, 1890-1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To John Hill Luther from Willison Bagby and Anne E. Luther, 1899, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther from Zollie Luther, 1881-1884 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - To John Hill Luther, Anne Jaudon Luther, and Anne Luther Bagby from Zollie Luther, 1884-1887 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - To John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther from Zollie Luther, 1887-1892 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - To John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther from John Hill Luther, Jr., 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - To John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther from John Hill Luther, Jr., 1890, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - To John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther from John Hill Luther, Jr., 1891, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - To John Hill Luther Jr. from Anne Luther Bagby, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther Outgoing Correspondence, 1872, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - To Alice Jaudon Smith from Anne Luther Bagby, Zollie Luther Jones, Alice Bagby, Doris Jones, and Grace Gooda, 1905-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Literary Productions, 1821-1939; 2
    Much of the material in this subseries was created by or about John Hill Luther and includes his sermon notes, journals, essays, and poems. There are also Baylor Female College rosters from John Hill Luther and his daughter Anne Luther Bagby's involvement with the school. Zollie Luther Jones, daughter of John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther, is represented in this subseries in her published writings and other poetry.
    - Family Histories: Autobiography of John Hill Luther: (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Family Histories: Autobiography of John Hill Luther: (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Family Histories: Diary of John HIll Luther, 1903 January-July (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Family Histories: Biographical Materials for John Hill Luther and Anne Jaudon Luther, 1884-1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Family Histories: Biographical Materials for John Hill Luther, Anne Jaudon Luther, and Zollie Luther Jones, 1902; 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Baylor Female College: Rosters: (1 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Baylor Femaile College: Rosters: (2 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Baylor Female College: Rosters: (3 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Baylor Female College: Circulars: (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Baylor Female College: Circulars: (2 of 2), undated (Box 126 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Speeches: John Hill Luther: (1 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Speeches: John Hill Luther: (2 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Speeches: John Hill Luther: (3 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Speeches: John Hill Luther: Baylor Female College: (1 of 3), circa 1886-1891 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Speeches: John Hill Luther: Baylor Female College: (2 of 3), circa 1886-1891 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Speeches: John Hill Luther: Baylor Female College: (3 of 3), circa 1886-1891 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther: Article on Anne Luther Bagby, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther: "It's a Girl": (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther: "It's a Girl": (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther: "The Bullfight", undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther: General, 1890-1891 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther, Jr.: School Papers: (1 of 3), 1890-1891 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther, Jr.: School Papers: (2 of 3), 1890-1891 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Essays: John Hill Luther, Jr.: School Papers: (3 of 3), 1890-1891 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Journals: John Hill Luther, 1886-1893 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Journals: John Hill Luther, 1894 January-1895 March (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Journals: John Hill Luther, 1895 April-1896 November (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notebooks: General, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Notebooks: John Hill Luther, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Sermons: John Hill Luther: Theology Lectures, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Sermons: John Hill Luther: Theology Lectures: (1 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Sermons: John Hill Luther: Theology Lectures: (2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Sermons: John Hill Luther: Notes: (1 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sermons: John Hill Luther: Notes: (2 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Sermons: John Hill Luther: Notes: (3 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Poems: Old Baylor and Other Poems by John Hill Luther, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Poems: Booklet, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Poems, 1821-1902 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Poems, 1846-1939 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Poems, 1869-1892 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Published Material of Zollie Luther Jones and John Hill Luther, 1897, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Legal Documents, 1888-1901; 3
    This subseries consists of two folders of legal documents, including materials related to Memorial Baptist Church.
    - Certified Documents, 1888-1891 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Memorial Baptist Church, 1900-1901 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Bagby Papers, 1843-1993; 2; 17 document boxes and 2 oversized boxes and 2 oversized folders.
  This series contains 17 boxes of correspondence and literary productions created by or about the Bagby family. Prominent themes in this series include education and Bagby family history. Materials about the Bagby family's mission work and family heritage are represented in the various manuscripts of Bagbys of Brazil and other writings about the Bagby family legacy.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  16 mm motion picture film; Cassette tape
  - Correspondence, 1868-1993; 1
    The bulk of the correspondence in this subseries is to Anne Luther Bagby and William Buck Bagby from various family members. There is also correspondence written to Alice Bagby Smith before her marriage in 1922 to Harley Smith. Correspondence to Alice Bagby Smith after her marriage is in Series III, Smith Papers, subseries Correspondence.
    - To Anne Luther Bagby, 1880-1914 (Box 126 OVZ, Folder 2)
    - To and from Anne Luther Bagby and John Hill Luther, 1881-1884 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from John Hill Luther, 1881-1883 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from John Hill Luther, 1882-1884 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - To William Buck Bagby and Anne Luther Bagby from John Hill Luther, 1886-1889 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from John Hill Luther, 1881-1902 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from John Hill Luther, 1888-1902 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from John Hill Luther, 1891-1898 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from Anne Jaudon Luther, 1881-1890 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from Anne Jaudon Luther, 1882-1892 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from Anne Jaudon Luther, 1884-1889 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from Anne Jaudon Luther, 1886-1889 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from Anne Jaudon Luther, 1887-1916 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - To Anne Luther Bagby from Anne Jaudon Luther, 1888, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - To William Buck Bagby and Anne Luther Bagby from Alice Bagby, 1906-1908 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - To William Buck Bagby and Anne Luther Bagby from Alice Bagby, 1908-1915 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - To William Buck Bagby and Anne Luther Bagby from Alice Bagby, 1914-1918, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - To William Buck Bagby and Anne Luther Bagby from Alice Bagby, 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 14)